Hello everyone and welcome to English Pot.
My name is Marco.
My name is Katherine
and today we have part
two of our series about
small talk in English.
That's right. So as we mentioned
small talk are very short,
quick conversations about
everyday things like the weather
and usually have this with a
colleague very quickly or a friend maybe.
Yeah, maybe not someone
you know very well too.
Exactly.
So we're going to take a look at part two.
Why don't we listen to the
dialogue and see what's going on?
So, Michelle, let me
introduce you to Maria.
She's my colleague from
Brazil. Maria, this is Michelle.
Hi Michelle. So what do you do here in
Shanghai? I mean, what work do you do?
I work in advertising right now. How about
you? I'm actually in the wine business.
Oh, that sounds really
great. I love wine myself.
Is this your first time
to Shanghai, Maria?
No. Actually, I often visit. I usually come
to China for business at least once a year.
Also, I love the restaurants in Shanghai.
So that's a good reason to come. Me too.
Actually, there's a great
Brazilian restaurant I recommend.
I mean, the food is delicious
but the service isn't so good.
I often like to get together with
friends and have a great barbecue there.
We should go there together sometime.
Wonderful idea. I'd love that.
All right, we're back.
So now let's take a look
at some of these very
interesting phrases we
find in this dialogue
in language takeaway.
Language takeaway. So
the first phrase we have
today is from the first
sentence of this dialogue.
James says, "So, Michelle,
let me introduce you to Maria.
" That's right. So we have the phrase
"introduce someone to" or "introduce you to.
" Okay, let me introduce
you to this person.
So Marco, let me
introduce you to my friend.
Right. And this is
something that you say when
you want to tell the
person, look, I'm going,
you're going to meet someone new.
Let me introduce you to my friend, Sally.
And this is very important because
it's polite and it's a way for you to say,
okay, you two don't
know each other.
Here, this is, you know,
this person's name.
This is this person's name.
It's very important when you
are introducing people or
when you're in a situation
with two people who
don't know each other.
That's right, exactly. So let
me introduce you to someone.
Now, another key
question here, I think
probably one of the key
questions when you meet
someone new, you're
talking small talk, short
conversation, what do you
do here or what do you do?
What do you do? So this
might sound like a very
strange question. What do
you do? Do you watch TV?
Do you like to eat food? No, but
this means what job do you do?
Right. What type
of work do you do?
Okay. So Marco, what do you do? I
host an English podcast. All right. Me too.
So this is the question.
Now, don't get confused
and remember that
this is the typical way of
asking someone.
What is their job?
If you say, what is your job
or what is your occupation?
It's too formal and it's kind
of awkward. I don't think
anyone has ever asked
me, what is your occupation?
No, I rarely say that. I
almost always say, what
do you do or maybe what
type of work do you do?
Or what business
are you in? Okay.
So this is our next phrase
actually. Right. If someone asks
you what business are
you in or what industry
are you in, you would
say like in this case,
Maria, she is in the
wine business. Okay.
I'm in the wine business.
That means that my job
has to do with
selling or buying wine.
So if we replace the noun
wine with something else, for
example, clothing, I'm
in the clothing business
or I'm in the cheese
business. Exactly.
You can basically change it
with anything with any product.
I guess if you sell
computers, I'm in the
computer business or if
you have anything to do
with computers, you can say
I'm in the computer business.
All right. So that's great.
I'm in the business. Exactly.
All right. So now we know what
the person does. We
continue asking questions.
You know, we're interested.
We want to keep the
conversation going
a little while longer.
We say, oh, wow, that's
really great. I love wine myself.
Then we ask, is this your
first time to Shanghai?
Okay. So is this your first time
to Shanghai or in Shanghai?
That means is this your first time
to visit Shanghai? That's right. Now,
the preposition here
is always confusing for
an ESL learner because
sometimes do you say,
is this your first
time in Shanghai?
Is this your first time on Shanghai?
Now we're saying to Shanghai.
So in this case or in this type
of question, both are correct.
Is this your first
time in Shanghai?
Is this your first time
to Shanghai? All right.
So I could also say, you
know, if we're in Chicago,
hey, Marco, is this your
first time in Chicago?
But I have to ask if
we are in that city.
I can't say, okay, I'm
in Chicago today, but
Marco, is this your
first time in New York?
Because we're not in New
York right now. Exactly.
That could be confusing. So
remember, when you ask this
question, you're asking about
where you are today right now.
Exactly. Very good.
So on that note,
let's take a break. Let's
listen to the dialogue
again and we'll be back
with some more phrases.
So Michelle, let me
introduce you to Maria.
She's my colleague from
Brazil. Maria, this is Michelle.
Hi, Michelle. So what do you do here in
Shanghai? I mean, what work do you do?
I work in advertising right now. How about
you? I'm actually in the wine business.
Oh, that sounds really
great. I love wine myself.
Is this your first time
to Shanghai, Maria?
No. Actually, I often visit. I usually come
to China for business at least once a year.
Also, I love the restaurants in Shanghai.
So that's a good reason to come. Me too.
Actually, there's a great
Brazilian restaurant I recommend.
I mean, the food is delicious,
but the service isn't so good.
I often like to get together with
friends and have a great barbecue there.
We should go there together
sometime. Wonderful idea. I'd love that.
All right, let's take a look at three more
key phrases on fluency builder part two.
Fluency builder. So one
phrase that we heard from
this, when things started
to get a little bit more
personal, Michelle
said, I often like to get
together with friends. So
this phrase here is to get
together with friends.
So to get together means
to be united or go
with friends somewhere.
That's right. So we could also
use the phrase to hang out.
This means you're not
doing anything in particular.
You're not cooking
or swimming or,
you know, going shopping,
but it just means you're
together with your friends.
You could be doing anything.
Right. Exactly. So
even if you want to ask
your friend or colleague,
hey, do you want to get
together after work and
have a couple of drinks?
All right, that means
would you like to hang out
or would you like to go
somewhere for a drink?
It's very informal and it's not romantic.
Right. It's just with friends.
Exactly. So if you ask
someone to get together
sometime, it doesn't
mean let's go out on a date.
It just means, you
know, let's hang out.
Let's hang out. Let's
be friends. Okay.
Now, so they were talking
about a Brazilian restaurant
and James said, Hey, you know,
we should go there sometime.
Okay. We should go there together
sometime is even like more personal.
This is a really common phrase.
And one that you guys should
remember as a phrase. Okay.
We should go there sometime.
That means that I would like to make
plans with you to go to this restaurant.
Right. Exactly. Now,
if you notice the word
sometime is separated,
you have some and then
apart. The other word is time. So it's very
different from sometimes. Don't confuse it.
What we're saying here is when you have
time, when I have time, we should go there.
It's almost like saying
one time or in the future.
Sometimes it's
different. It's like,
I brush my teeth sometimes. That
means not very often. No, that's not true.
But I would like to go
there sometime means,
you know, it's, it's
a little bit vague.
I don't say when, but I
would like to in the future.
Exactly. And Michelle
agrees. She says, wow,
it's a wonderful idea. I'd love that. Okay.
This is another great phrase. Remember this
as a phrase. Would you
like to go see a movie?
I'd love that. I'd love
that. So I'd love that.
I'd love to. These are ways
of saying, I like the idea.
Let's do it. Mm hmm. Exactly.
So it's usually in response
to an invitation or suggestion.
Very good. All right.
So let's take a look
at our dialogue again and review
everything and we'll be back in a bit.
So Michelle, let me introduce you to
Maria. She's my colleague from Brazil.
Maria, this is Michelle. Hi Michelle.
So what do you do here in Shanghai?
I mean, what work do you do?
I work in advertising right now.
How about you? I'm
actually in the wine business.
Oh, that sounds really great.
I love wine myself. Is this your
first time to Shanghai, Maria?
No. Actually, I often visit. I usually come
to China for business at least once a year.
Also, I love the
restaurants in Shanghai.
So that's a good
reason to come. Me too.
Actually, there's a great
Brazilian restaurant I recommend.
I mean, the food
is delicious, but the
service isn't so good. I
often like to get together
with friends and have
a great barbecue there.
We should go there together sometime.
Wonderful idea. I'd love that.
All right. So as we
can see, it's very quick,
small conversation, but
very good phrases to talk
to a stranger to start
up a small conversation.
I think these are great
too, Marco, because if
you're learning English
and you want to practice
your speaking skills,
you're not going to have
many people to talk
about deep things with.
So it's great to use with strangers
or with people in your office.
That's right. And
these are common
typical questions. And they're
also appropriate to ask someone.
So obviously, if you meet someone new,
you're not going to ask them how much money
they make because that's
kind of inappropriate in
Western culture. That's
right. So what we've taught
you here are very polite,
very common phrases.
We hope, hope, hope that
you'll go out and practice these.
If you have questions
or comments, don't
hesitate to leave them for
us. Our website is EnglishPod.
com. All right. We'll
see you guys there. Bye.